Guide to the George Amberg and Robert Gessner Papers 1913-1978 (Bulk 1940-1970) MC 199
New York University Archives
George Amberg and Robert Gessner Papers
Bulk, 1940-1970
1913-1978
MC 199
New York University Archives
10.5 linear feet (18 boxes)
The George Amberg and Robert Gessner Papers contains the personal and professional papers of George Amberg and Robert Gessner. The bulk of the collection was created by Gessner. The collection documents the development of university film education, the formation of The Society of Cinematologists, and Gessner's career as a screenwriter, novelist, and poet. Amberg's work at New York University, the University of Minnesota, and the Minneapolis School of Art is also documented.
Gessner, Robert, 1907-1968
Arrangement
All series except Series IV (Records of The Society of Cinematologists) are arranged alphabetically. Series IV is arranged chronologically. When there was an original folder title, it is shown in quotes; otherwise, a title has been assigned to the folder based on its contents.
Original order has been maintained within each folder. The collection arrived at the NYU Archives in folders labeled with an alphanumeric code (A1, A2) on a label that obscured handwritten folder titles. There were no discernible series, and the creator's original order was not evident at the folder level; however, there was evidence that within each folder the original order had been maintained. The alphanumeric code has been written on the folders.
To gain control over the collection, it was grouped into 8 series:
I, Correspondence
II, Subject files, projects, proposals, and course materials on film and film education
III, Biographical materials
IV, Records of the Society of Cinematologists
V, Writings
VI, Films
VII, Non-English Material
VIII, Scrapbooks
Related Material
The Robert Gessner Papers at the New York Public Library
Robert Gessner papers, ca. 1956-1968 The Fales Collection of English and American Literature at NYU
Contains rare editions of Gessner's published works, including:
Broken arrow
Upsurge
The Moving Image; A Guide to Cinematic Literacy
Here is my home
Treason
Youth is the Time
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the material was created by Robert Gessner.
This collection covers the development of film education in the United States, The Society of Cinematologists, and Robert Gessner's career as an educator and writer. In addition to film, Robert Gessner wrote about Native American life in the United States, anti-Semitism, and labor issues.
Series I: Correspondence is divided into two subseries:
Sub-series A Amberg Correspondence: The bulk of the material is correspondence related to Amberg's film project "The Captive Eye," including notes from significant film industry figures regarding permission to use their work in the project.
Sub-series B Gessner Correspondence: Contains Gessner's professional correspondence related to film and film education, the cinema program at NYU, film festivals, and publishing.
Correspondence that was originally filed with subject files is in Series II, correspondence of The Society of Cinematologists is in Series IV, and correspondence originally filed with writings is in Series V.
Series II: Subject files, projects, proposals, and course materials on film and film education.
Contains both Amberg and Gessner subject files. The bulk of the material consists of published articles, press releases, clippings, and notes on films and directors, film and television education, film production, and film festivals that Amberg and Gessner used in their work. The series also contains proposals, notes, working papers, and some correspondence regarding projects including the American Cinema and Television Academy, and NYU's closed circuit television courses. Course materials include syllabi, exams, slide sheets, and lecture notes for courses in Cinema and the Humanities.
Series III: Biographical Materials is divided into two subseries:
Sub-series A: Amberg Biographical Material includes Amberg's curricula vitae from 1968
Sub-series B: Gessner Biographical Material includes reviews of Gessner's work, articles about his career, curricula vitae, and other biographical material.
Series IV: Records of the Society of Cinematologists
The Society of Cinematologists (now the Society for Cinema and Media Studies) is a professional organization founded in 1956 at MoMA's Third Annual Conference on Cinema. Its members include film educators, filmmakers, historians, critics and scholars. This series contains Society of Cinematologists board minutes, newsletters, and correspondence from the organization's founding and its early years, and Reminiscences of a Cinematologist, a narrative account of the Society by Robert Gessner.
Series V: Writings is divided into two subseries:
Sub-series A: The Writings of George Amberg includes Amberg's typescripts of screenplays and articles on film and ballet
Sub-series B: The Writings of Robert Gessner includes Gessner's manuscripts, typescripts, notebooks, and working papers for novels, poetry, screenplays, and articles. Also includes related correspondence as originally filed.
Series VI: Films
Nine cans of 35mm film elements, which are currently being processed and evaluated by the NYU library's Barbara Goldsmith Preservation and Conservation Department.
Series VII: Non-English Material
One box of unprocessed material including film posters, articles, and clippings in German, French, and Italian.
Series VIII: Scrapbooks
Two leather-bound scrapbooks contain articles, ephemera, and correspondence regarding the publication and critical reception of Robert Gessner's novels Traitor and Youth Is the Time.
Biographies
Robert Gessner
Robert Gessner was a pioneer in film education, a film professor at NYU, and a published poet, novelist, and screenwriter.
Gessner was born October 23, 1907, in Escanaba, Michigan. He received a B.A. from the University of Michigan in 1929 and an M.A. from Columbia University in 1930. Gessner started teaching at NYU in 1930, replacing Thomas Wolfe as an English professor. In the early 1930s he was a screenwriter in Hollywood, and his book "Massacre" was made into a film by Warner Brothers in 1934. Gessner began teaching cinema studies in 1935 in NYU's Division of General Education, and in 1939 he taught the first cinema course for credit in a liberal arts college, "Cinema as a Literary Art," at Washington Square College. Gessner founded the Motion Picture Department at NYU in 1941, the first four-year film curriculum leading to a B.A. degree in motion picture studies in the United States.
Gessner's articles on cinema were published in The New York Times, Variety, Theater Arts, and other publications. His published books include: Massacre; A Survey of Today's American Indian (1931), Broken Arrow (1933), Upsurge (1933), Some of My Best Friends are Jews (1936), Here is my Home (1941), Treason (1944), Youth is the Time (1945) and The Moving Image, A Guide to Cinematic Literacy (1968). He won The New Republic International poetry contest in 1934. In 1959 he became the founding president of The Society of Cinematologists (now called the Society for Cinema and Media Studies) a professional organization of film educators, filmmakers, historians, critics, and scholars. He was the first visiting professor to lecture in Israel (at Hebrew University), and he also lectured at film centers around the world, including universities in Rome, Vienna, Poland, Paris, Yugoslavia, and England. He received two Ford Foundation grants: one to produce a series of experimental films at Harvard university in 1962-63, and one to lecture at film academies in Eastern Europe in 1962. In 1964 he was Chairman of the Jury at the International Film Festival in Cork, Ireland, and appeared on the CBS television program Camera Three. In 1966 he was a fellow at Kings College, Cambridge University. He finished his book The Moving Image, A Guide to Cinematic Literacy before he died in June 1968.
George Amberg
George Amberg received his Ph.D. from the University of Cologne in 1930. He was a curator in the Department of Theater Arts at the Museum of Modern Art (New York) from 1943-1948 and also worked as a photographer. He taught in the Division of General Education at NYU from 1948-1952, establishing the first course in experimental film ("New Frontiers in the Cinema") in 1950. He became a professor at the University of Minnesota and the Minneapolis School of the Arts, teaching a variety of humanities courses. His published works include: Art in Modern Ballet (1946), The Theater of Eugene Berman (1947), and Ballet in America: The Emergence of an American Art (1949), as well as many articles in publications such as Theater Arts, Interiors, and Graphis. He returned to NYU in 1966, becoming a professor of Cinema and the director of the graduate Cinema Program. In 1968 he became President of The Society for Cinematologists. He edited the encyclopedic New York Times Film Reviews, 1913-1970 (1971).
Sources:
The George Amberg and Robert Gessner Papers
"Robert Gessner, Film Professor" published in the New York Times June 17, 1968
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. Except for Series VIII: Scrapbooks, this collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
The Robert Gessner Papers were donated to NYU by Doris Gessner in 1969. George Amberg oversaw the donation of the Gessner papers to NYU, and his papers were eventually intermixed with Gessner's. The George Amberg and Robert Gessner papers were transferred to the NYU Archives from the George Amberg Memorial Film Study Center (Tisch School of the Arts) in 2006. Robert Gessner's scrapbooks, comprising Series VIII of the collection, were transferred from the Fales Library and Special Collections at NYU in 2010.
Amberg, George, 1901-; Society for Cinema and Media Studies.; Society for Cinema Studies.; Society of Cinematologists.; American literature |y 20th century.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Film criticism.; Manuscripts (document genre).; Motion picture plays |x History and criticism; Motion pictures (visual works).; Notebooks; Notes.; Reviews (document genre).
- Series I: Correspondence.
  - Subseries A: Amberg Correspondence
    - "The Age of Film" - Amberg/Lanier Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      barcode#:31142042277924
    - "The Captive Eye", 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "The Captive Eye", 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Gessner Correspondence
    - "Belgrade", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Burton, French 1968", Nov-67-Dec-67 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Cambridge", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Camera III (Television show), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes Photographs
    - "Canfield", Jan-46-Feb-46 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Comm. Int. Ex. Persons", 1962, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Comm. Int. Ex. Persons", 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Cork 1964" (Film Festival) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Cork" (Film Festival), 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Curtis-Brown", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Davis, Hallie Flanagan, Jan-46-Feb-46 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Ford Foundation", 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Forrester, E.M.", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Gessner, Robert - Correspondence", Nov-67-Feb-68 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Guggenheim", 1957-1961, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Jones, Joe", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lang, Fritz, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "Manoogian - 1964", 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Massacre", 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      barcode#:31142042277932
    - Meredith, Burgess, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence from Untitled folder 1, 1939-1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence from Untitled folder 2, 1939-1948, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence from Untitled folder 3, Mar-64-Nov-64 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence from Untitled folder 4, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Mount-Woolfe", Jan-46 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "The Moving Image", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Moving Image Correspondence - 1968", 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Moving Image Correspondence - 1968", 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Nat. Cinema Proj.", 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "NYU - Mexico/Falk Letters", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Panofsky", 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Perkins, Maxwell, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Schulman, William", 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Scorsese, Martin, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Signature - Well Known", 1937-1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Notes from Walt Disney, Stanley Kramer, Carl Sandburg, and others
    - "Steele, Robert", 1964-1965, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Topelitz, Jerzy", 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Whitney, John", Jan-46 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Series II: Subject Files
  - Allen, Woody, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    barcode#:31142042277940
  - American Cinema Television Academy- Proposal and Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "ACTA" (American Cinema Television Academy), 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "American Council on Education", 1941-1942, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes Correspondence and Society of Cinematologists materials
  - Anger, Kenneth - Magick Lantern Cycle, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Arkin, Alan, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Art Films, 0000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes Amberg Correspondence
  - "Art in Progress (MoMA)", 1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Articles", 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Avery, Tex, 0000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Baillie, Bruce, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Barrault, Jean-Louis, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    barcode#:31142042277940 barcode#:31142042277940
  - "Bartholomew, David", 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - the Beatles, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Beatty, Warren, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Berkeley, Busby, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bogart, Humphrey, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Brakhage, Stan, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Breer, Robert, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bresson, Robert, 0000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Bridge San Luis Rey, The Informer", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    includes contact sheets, photographs and negatives
  - "Camera Three" ("Seven Faces of Time" episode), 31-May-64 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Transcript of Gessner's appearance on CBS television show
  - "Cinema 1968 - Reviews and odds and ends" (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Cinema Articles, 1947, 1950, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Cinematic Perception, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Cinema Reviews and Clippings, 0000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Closed Circuit Television for Teaching University Courses, and "Omnibus" 10-26, 1954-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    barcode#:31142042277957
  - Course Material - "56.0001, 56.0011", 0000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Course Material - Contemporary Cinema Spring 1971, 1962, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Course Material - Contemporary Cinema, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Course Material - "Gessner, Robert 049", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Course Material - Humanities 54 notes, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Course Material - Humanities Class notes, 0000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Course Material - Humanities class notes, exams, slide sheets, 1950-1956, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Course Material - Humanities, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Course Material - Literature and Cinema a proposal for an interdisciplinary course, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Course Material - "TMR-1 Outside Reading", 1955-1956, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Clair, Rene, 0000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Corman, Roger, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Cukor, George, 0000 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Demille, Cecil B., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Dennis, Sandy, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Deren, Maya, 0000 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Deville, Michel, 0000 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Donskoi, Mark, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Douglas, Kirk, 0000 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Dreyer, Carl Theodor, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Dwan, Allan, 0000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Edelstein, Robert, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Edwards, Blake, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    barcode#:31142042277965
  - Farrrow, Tisa, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fairbanks, Douglas, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Fields, W.C., 0000 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Film Festivals - photos, clippings, correspondence, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Film Index (Box 15, Folder 1)
    a set of index cards with film titles and short descriptions
  - Film Programs and notes, 1949-1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Film reviews and articles, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Film Stills - Contact Sheets and negatives, 0000 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Film Stills - Negatives, 0000 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Flaherty, Robert, 0000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Fonda, Henry, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Garbo" (film title), 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Garrel, Philippe, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Gould, Elliot, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Griffith, D.W., 0000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - International Industrial Film Festival Program, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - "New Years Eve" (Film title) - synopsis, script, and film stills, 0000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - "NY Film Festival 1963" (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - New York University, 1960, 1971, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Miscellaneous memos, film library index, Cinematheque schedule
  - New York University - Center for instructional television, Miscellaneous Educational television, 1956-1960 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - New York University - Closed Circuit Television courses, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "Ottawa Film Society", 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    barcode#:31142042277973
  - "Omnibus", 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    the first 26 programs
  - Omnibus Third Season, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Pacific Federation of Film Societies", 1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Pushkin", 0000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Screening Notes 1966-1967", 1964, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Toronto Film Society", 1967-1978 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - TV/Radio Workshop Film Catalog, 0000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Unesco Film Stills", 0000 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - "Unesco Film Stills", 0000 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Vadim, Roger, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "War and Peace" (Film) - Correspondence and related material, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "Zorns Lemma", 1970 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "Zulu", 0000 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Series III: Biographical Material
  - Amberg - Curriculum Vitae, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    barcode#:31142042277981
  - Gessner - Boston University inventory of Gessner materials, 0000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Gessner - "Biography", 1946-1964 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Gessner - Reviews of Gessner's writing, 1936-1968 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Newspaper clippings
- Series IV: Records of the Society of Cinematologists
  - "Reminiscences of a Cinematologist", 0000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Rosenthal Awards, 1957-1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Cinematology Soc.", 1961-1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Rosenthal - 1964", 0000 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "S.O.C. Nomenclature", 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Griffith, R." - Society of Cinematologists correspondence, Mar-64 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Kupier, John" - Society of Cinematologists correspondence, 0000 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "S.O.C. - 1964" (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "Council - 1964 - S.O.C." (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "S.O.C. - 1965" (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "International Representation", 1966 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Society of Cinematologists - Newsletter, Minutes, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Series V: Writings
  - Subseries A: Writings of George Amberg
    - "The Art of Persuasion", 0000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      barcode#:31142042277999
    - The Art of Persuasion, Discovery and Progress, Birth and Childhood of the Movies, The Film as Art, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - The Captive Eye: the Art of the Film, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "The Captive Eye", 1965 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The Film as Art, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Rigoletto, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Surrealism and Photography, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - The Visible World - An Essay on Visual Appreciation, New Frontiers in the Cinema, and research materials, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Subseries B: Writings of Robert Gessner
    - "Alberto", 1963 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - "Alberto Columbo Discovers America", 0000 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Annals of Crime, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "Art Versus Industry: a Re-examination", 0000 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - "Articles", 1940-1967 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      Includes 1967 biography and bibliography of Gessner
    - Behind the Ivy, 0000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      barcode#:31142042278005
    - "Big Dick", 1968 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Christopher Columbo: an original screen outline, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "Cinema Book", 1955, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - City College, 0000 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - "Copies of Articles", 0000 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Considerations for the Establishment of Motion Picture Courses in Colleges and Universities, 1946-1949 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - The Darkest Day, 0000 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - The Darkest Day, 0000 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Dick - Being the Hitherto Unpublished Campaign Biography of the Late Senator-elect Richard Pettijohn", 0000 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - The Double Jointed Southpaw, 0000 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - "ECL", 1953-1959 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      materials related to "The Democratic Man - Readings from Eduard C. Lindeman"
    - A Farce -- Fantasy, 0000 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      by Eleanor Daly and Robert Gessner
    - "The Faces of Time - 1962" (Box 9, Folder 14)
      Also called "The Seven Faces of Time" see box 10, folder 20 and 21
    - The Faces of Time, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      Also called "The Seven Faces of Time" see box 10
    - The Fruit Trees: a Tale for Television (synopsis), 0000 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - "Humanist" Faustus Goes to Hell in Technicolor, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - "The Handwriting on the Screen" and Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - "Heaven Bent for Election", 0000 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Hell Bent for Election: a Farce -- Fantasy, 0000 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - "International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences", 1966 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      barcode#:31142042278013
    - "Introducing Sixty", 1967 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - A Letter to the Enemy, Downtown Harvard Club, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Liberty to Love: a screenplay treatment, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      by G.W. Pabst and Robert Gessner
    - Liberty to Love: a screenplay treatment, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Love for Export, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Macbeth", 0000 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - The Motion Picture: a New Way of Storytelling, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - "The Movies are now Cinema", "Youth Locked Out", and clippings and correspondence related to National Council on the Arts grants to Cinema and Television, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - The Moving Image - "Book - Index", 0000 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - "The Night After Christmas", 0000 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - "Original Chapters 1-3" (Treason), 0000 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - The Parts of Cinema: a definition, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "Poetry", 1939-1963 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - "Poetry" (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Put Your Leg Over: an Original Treatment Based in Part on 'Bobby Butler' by George Bass, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - "Quisling", 0000 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Real Money: an Original Television Drama, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - The Return of the Native, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - In Search of the Third Eye: an Account of a Journey to Cinema Academies in Poland and Yugoslavia, 0000 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - "Seven Faces of Time", 0000 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - "7 Faces of Time", 1962-1964 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - See You Tomorrow: an original for TV, 0000 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      barcode#:31142042278021
    - "Sex Out of Focus", 1961 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      and related correspondence
    - "The Stranger Goes to Jail", 0000 (Box 11, Folder 3)